<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nathan Scully]]></title>
  <link href="http://nathanscully.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nathanscully.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-02T21:41:20+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://nathanscully.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nathan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A new language]]></title>
    <link href="http://nathanscully.github.com/blog/a-new-language/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-16T18:00:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nathanscully.github.com/blog/a-new-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After having a few moments over the last few months of &#8216;I need to learn something new&#8217; - I have decided to teach myself a new language/technology.</p>

<p>According to the internet I need to be learning&#8230; well, I just end up confused. Scala, clojure, ruby(well Ruby On Rails for something useful), javascript, functional, JVM based - it just gets silly. To make life simpler, I bit the bullet and just picked one that sounded interesting and I am going to stick with it and try a few projects. Then pick another and try and recreate the projects or just move onto new ones.</p>

<p>Node.js took my fancy - purely because I have used javascript in the past, I am interested in web applications and it just sounds like a different way of thinking than I am used to. I started a couple of helloworld tutorals and I have decided to stick to it(even though you see posts about [how terrible node.js is(http://dev.hasenj.org/post/31042963934/nodejs-hate)]).</p>

<p>Will it be the language of the future - maybe, javascript is pretty useful across both web and now thanks to node.js, the server. I really want to get into Google&#8217;s language <a href="www.golang.org">Go</a> - but that will be later!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nodepad - Node.js Appliction]]></title>
    <link href="http://nathanscully.github.com/blog/nodepad-node-dot-js-appliction/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-16T17:51:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nathanscully.github.com/blog/nodepad-node-dot-js-appliction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction:</h2>

<p>With my new motivation(and commitment) to learn Javascript - specifically the <a href="www.nodejs.org">node.js</a> platform I have been hunting for a few tutorials.</p>

<p>After completing some basic helloworld I found <a href="www.dailyjs.com">daily.js</a> and their <a href="http://dailyjs.com/2010/11/01/node-tutorial/">nodepad</a> application.</p>

<p>It was written a few years ago and is now out of date with versions, and likely syntax so I am going to go through the tutorial and write my own version. All credits to dailyjs for the original material.</p>

<p>Nodepad will be a simple web based notepad application built using node.js and taking advantage of the express framework</p>

<h2>Requirements:</h2>

<ul>
<li>Node.js - an obvious requirement!</li>
<li>MongoDB - a NoSQL database thats getting a good wraps across the interwebs</li>
<li>NPM - Node package manager - used to install and manage any additonal packages we require.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Setup:</h2>

<p>Make a new working directory:</p>

<pre><code>mkdir nodepad
</code></pre>

<p>Install express</p>

<pre><code>npm install -g express
</code></pre>

<p>The -g flag installs this globally, allowing us to setup a skeleton application:</p>

<pre><code>express nodepad
</code></pre>

<p>Change into the nodepad directory and install the dependencies</p>

<pre><code>npm install
</code></pre>

<p>Update the package.json to include the required dependencies:</p>

<pre><code>{
  "name": "nodepad",
  "version": "0.0.1",
  "private": true,
  "scripts": {
    "start": "node app"
  },
  "dependencies": {
    "express": "3.1.0",
    "jade": "*",
    "less": "*",
    "expresso": "*",
    "mongoose": "*"
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Run the skeleton application and view it on http://localhost:3000/:</p>

<pre><code>node app.js
</code></pre>

<p>Close the process and then setup a mongodb database:
in a new terminal start the mongodb server:</p>

<pre><code>mongod
</code></pre>

<p>connect via:</p>

<pre><code>mongo
</code></pre>

<p>Create a new nodepad db:</p>

<pre><code>use nodepad
</code></pre>

<h2>Application:</h2>

<p>Setup our first data model - we will use mongoose to wrap a class around our mongodb database. Save the following as models.js in the root of the nodepad folder.</p>

<pre><code>var mongoose = require('mongoose');

mongoose.model('Document', {
  properties: ['title', 'data', 'tags'],

  indexes: [
    'title'
  ]
});

exports.Document = function(db) {
  return db.model('Document');
};
</code></pre>

<p>We can now use the model via the following in our app.js file:</p>

<pre><code>db = mongoose.connect('mongodb://localhost/nodepad')
Document = require('./models.js').Document(db);
</code></pre>

<p>Be sure to add the mongoose dependency to the list of required modules:</p>

<pre><code>mongoose = require('mongoose');
</code></pre>

<p>Add the following  config to our app.js. This will enable us to use less to complie our css</p>

<pre><code>app.configure(function(){
...
  app.use(express.compiler({ src : __dirname + '/public', enable: ['less']}));
});
</code></pre>

<p>This completes the basic setup of our application. The next post will develop the application futher.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[And so it beings]]></title>
    <link href="http://nathanscully.github.com/blog/and-so-it-beings/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-16T15:15:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nathanscully.github.com/blog/and-so-it-beings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been thinking about writing for a while. By &#8216;writing&#8217; I mean dumping my thoughts and what I have been doing whilst consuming time.</p>

<p>This is a bit of a motivational project, self improvement even. I am dyslexic, so the thought of writing large chunks of text general makes me uncomfortable. But the more I write the better I get and the more succinct I am in conveying my thoughts.</p>

<p>I also am a scatter brain. I can focus and work for hours on end and forget what I started out trying to accomplish. The worst is when I work on something and find a useful tidbit of information that I want to reuse 3 months later but can&#8217;t for the life of me remember. This blog will server as a purpose to document and mamange my tidbits, and for me to have something to show myself what I have been working on. I think everyone needs to remind themsevles what they have accomplished - it is easy to only see what you havent finished, or even started.</p>

<p>Who am I? A 24 year old from Sydney, Australia. I studied Design Computing with the hopes of becoming an intermediary between Creative and Technical people. A sort of translator between someone who speaks colours and someone who speaks code. For the last 3 years I have been working for a small IT Consultancy company that develops and integrates software and systems around telecommunications and Contact Centres / Call Centres. My role is as a Application Designer/ Voice Consultant/Software Developer/SysAdmin/PreSales/Project Manager - basically just what needs to be done on the day. 90% of my work is developing IVRs(Interactive Voice Response) - Those hated telephone systems that ask you to press 1, press 2 or say what you want. The beauty of the IVRs I develop is that I have full end to end control of the scope, design, development, deployment and maintaince. You learn alot, and very very quickly.</p>

<p>I code in Java, I know - how uncool&#8230; Java does what I want it to do, all my clients are large enterprises (Banks generally) so Java plays very nice with their systems. But it is bloated, and the more I play with other languages(Scala/Javascript/Node.js/Rails/Ruby), I am realising there is so much more out there. I have experience in web lanaguages but I am starting to branch out and learn new things. All these languages/technologies are all getting me excited about creating things for myself, not just for a client.</p>

<p>I have set this blog up using <a href="www.octopress.org">Octopress</a>. This is a blog framework for <a href="http://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a>. So far I love the concept - get rid of the web front end and silly post creation interfaces and just type the post in a text editor of choice. All this is pushed up to github which saves me worring about keeping me a copy and finding hosting.</p>

<p>I am hoping this easy format will encourage me to keep writing. I am going to start simple and document some tutorials and projects i will be working on. My goal is to really force myself to partake in &#8216;weekend&#8217; projects - little apps that I can knock up in a few days.</p>

<p>And so it begins&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
